one in three of you watching this video
right now has a parasite in your brain
that is altering your preferences
behavior and personality seriously when
infected individuals are compared with
non-infected individuals the infected
are found to be more aggressive
impulsive and neurotic additionally
infected men are found to be more cold
and suspicious of others while infected
women are the opposite tending to be
more warm trusting and outgoing today
we're we're going to dive deep into all
aspects of this mind controlling
parasite how it functions how terrified
we need to be and how it may have played
a role in shaping human culture but
first we have to say its name Toxoplasma
gandi is a microparasitic protoo meaning
it's a small harmful single cell
eukarion just as a reminder we and every
other animal are ukar meaning tandi is
more closely related to us than any
bacteria despite looking the the way it
does if you take any human population
around the world you'll find Toxoplasma
infecting 10% all the way to 95% of the
population it was even found preserved
on an ancient Egyptian mummy so it's
likely been evolving alongside us for
thousands perhaps millions of years and
it doesn't stop there toxo infects
nearly every warm-blooded mammal and
most birds to similar percentages making
it arguably the most serop prevalent
pathogen of all all time now Toxoplasma
infections can lead to a disease called
toxoplasmosis but in most cases it's
just a latent infection causing no
symptoms that harm the host at least
that's what it wants us to think like
most life te gandi really has one goal
to get laid and it's evolved to do that
in One Singular environment the
intestines of cats any feel line from
Tabby to Tiger is a worthy host because
they're the only mammals that have the
right around housing acid in their
intestines which the Toxoplasma need to
sexually reproduce when they mate they
produce thousands of uh I never know how
to say this oo cysts or oos cysts really
I think we need an exorcist because
thousands of these little demons are
shed into the cat's poop and guess what
poop goes everywhere animals eat it they
track it around it seeps into the soil
it watches over you while you sleep at
night you can't escape poop and since
these cysts last for years on surfaces
without dying this is how Toxoplasma
becomes so widespread also this is why
you shouldn't clean cat litter while
you're pregnant while toxo doesn't
really harm us it can harm reproductive
function so handling cat poop is a
really easy way to contract congenital
toxoplasmosis but if cats are the main
host for Toxoplasma why does it infect
other animals at all rodents with
toxoplasmosis behave incredibly
strangely they will hiss and pounce at
cats often to their own demise normally
when you're a mouse and you're mousing
about you rely on your sense of smell a
lot and certain smells say stinky cat
piss for example are recognized as
dangerous so when you smell it you think
ah Predator nearby got to run got to
hide but when you're a mouse with
toxoplasmosis you'll instead find
yourself incredibly attracted to the
smell of that piss the odor is just
magnificent so Splendid and divine you
can't help but follow its deliciousness
and then you die because a cat just
found you hanging around its urinal this
is called the Fatal Attraction
phenomenon because Toxoplasma is
literally inverting an evolved fear
response into one of Attraction
ultimately leading to the mouse's death
it's turning a healthy piss phobia into
a deadly piss Kink I'm sorry I I
shouldn't have said that naturally once
this was discovered someone wanted to
see if the same thing happens in humans
so a study took urine samples from cats
horses dogs tigers and hyenas then had
humans rate the pleasantness of the
various scents they found that men with
Toxoplasma infections found the smell of
cat urine significantly more pleasant
than non-infected men while infected
women found it less Pleasant than
non-infected women again we see these
opposite effects from Toxoplasma in men
and women like how men's personalities
become more cold when infected while
women's become more warm all of the
other urine samples in this experiment
were rated the exact same level of
pleasantness between infected and
non-infected groups except for hyenas
which actually had the same results as
cats but with a much weaker Trend
scientists have observed that mice with
toxoplasmosis show no fear of cats even
after their infection clears meaning
it's causing a permanent change in their
brain as if flipping a switch that
completely overrides a rodent's natural
instinct turning it functionally
suicidal nobody understands the exact
mechanisms in how Toxoplasma does this
but one study compared the brains of
infected and non-infected mice and found
differences in dopamine expression of
course it'd be dopamine it always ends
up being dopamine but yeah Toxoplasma
may be using host neurotransmitters to
essentially rewire Pathways in the brain
alongside this toxo also increases
aggression so you end up with mice that
are running up and attacking their
natural Predators clearly this is no Co
Co incidence because after the mouse
gets itself eaten the toxo very
conveniently ends up in the place it
wants to be so it seems that t gandi has
adapted to mind control rodents in order
to increase its likelihood of
reproduction rodents here are an
intermediate host for Toxoplasma while
cats are the definitive host previously
on this channel I used the example of
the green banded brood a flatworm that
infects snails by pulsing up and down
their eye stocks this mimics cat
caterpillars so that birds will be
enticed to find and eat the snail and
the Brut saach is then able to reproduce
inside the bird it seems there's a trend
among parasites to manipulate their
intermediate hosts in an incredibly
invasive way just to get them eaten by a
definitive host that they really don't
harm in a similar capacity and this is
probably why we aren't nearly as
affected by Toxoplasma as myar we aren't
as good of an intermediate host because
we're a lot less likely to get eaten by
a cat and yet Toxoplasma continues to
infect us and a bunch of animals that
never interact with cats at all is it
waiting for the perfect opportunity to
mutate and control us then take over the
world that would be scary and I won't
say impossible but it's highly unlikely
considering there wouldn't really be any
evolutionary pressure for that to happen
so you probably don't have to worry
about this becoming the zombie virus
probably a better explanation is that
there is no good explanation mammals are
all kind of the same we have the same
internal organs the bones in our fingers
are the same bones that stretch out into
bat wings or close down into whale fins
and if you go down into the level of
neurons in the brain you literally can't
tell the difference between a mouse's
brain and a human one so it's possible
that Toxoplasma adapted solely for
rodents and cats but because we're just
so similar to them it happens to be able
to infect us too on the other hand
Toxoplasma might infect us as a
roundabout way to get to a cat like sure
a moose will probably never get eaten by
a cat but if Toxoplasma can infect the
Moose it can be released in its poop
then get eaten by a mouse which is then
killed by a bird which then flies across
the world and is hunted by a lion it
isn't as if Toxoplasma is in much of a
hurry to get to a cat as I said it can
survive for a really long time outside
on surfaces and even in hosts that it
can't sexually reproduce within it can
still asexually reproduce creating
copies of itself to indefinitely either
way infecting multiple species is just
something that pathogens do some of the
worst diseases in history jumped to
humans from animals the black plague
Ebola covid-19 allegedly did we ever
figure that out by the way like was it a
bat penglin a lab I don't know but maybe
we should consider ourselves lucky that
Toxoplasma isn't nearly as dangerous to
us as any of these though it's actually
because it's not dangerous that it's
able to spread as much as it has
remember during Co when we figured out
that some people were asymptomatic and
were spreading Co despite not having any
of the symptoms themselves it made the
whole thing a lot trickier to contain
because it's hard to stop the spread
when you don't know who's spreading it
since we're asymptomatic to Toxoplasma
infections it spreads Among Us without
any resistance which is probably why 30%
of the world has it and has no idea it
even exists as I've been editing this
video I kept coming across more crazy
things things about Toxoplasma some of
which I just had to include first of all
it's linked with schizophrenia OCD
bipolar disorder and most recently like
a month ago as of recording this a paper
came out finding a positive relationship
between Toxoplasma infections and
anxiety disorders now all of this is
correlational data which means it's not
confirmed that Toxoplasma leads to
mental disorders but looking into this
further is definitely necessary so we
can see the full scope of what tox is
doing to our brain also since toxo is
able to bury itself and stay dormant in
your brain some people want to
bioengineer it for medical purposes so
literally bringing medicine into your
brain via a brain parasite it sounds
pretty crazy but this is a potentially
very promising technique and it could
totally change how we treat brain
injuries and mental disorders in the
future but of course it's very early in
development we likely won't see it
implemented for quite some time if it
even works at all talko plasma has
infected us for a long long time so just
how much has it impacted us as a species
over the years would an early group that
was infected with Toxoplasma develop
more aggressive traditions and
Lifestyles compared to a non-infected
one would the seemingly gender dependent
effects create exaggerated gender roles
in an infected Society let me know what
you think in the comments below because
your guess is as good as mine some
people suggest that since we've
confirmed Toxoplasma was in ancient
Egypt and that Toxoplasma makes you like
cats that Toxoplasma was the reason that
ancient Egyptians woried cats it's a fun
thought but I don't really buy it for
one people finding cat urine less bad
than usual is not the same as liking
cats more than usual but also the
Egyptians worshiped a lot of animals
besides cats and not all of them have a
corresponding parasite to explain their
Divinity I mean unless we just don't
know about that yet my last video about
parasite ended up getting demonetized
hopefully the same won't happen with
this one but YouTube's Advertiser safe
guidelines can be really vague I like
talking about these disturbing yet
important topics that I feel no one else
is really talking about so it's a real
bummer to have the income on these
videos slashed especially because uh I'm
a recent graduate and I don't make that
much income so I'm launching YouTube
memberships to see if that might help if
you want to learn about what you get if
you're a member you can click the join
button below to see what I'm offering
otherwise just watching another video of
mine helps me tremendously so consider
checking out this one up here and uh
thanks for watching